Tasker H. Bliss papers M2123
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Tasker H. Bliss papers
circa 1900-1923
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
James Cummins Bookseller
Bliss, Tasker Howard, 1853-1930
M2123
0.834 linear feet 2 manuscript boxes
Content Description
The materials consist of correspondence and related documents from his time as Collector of Customs for Cuba, personal and administrative correspondence received while on the Army War College Board, drafts and finished texts of speeches, book reviews, military reports, expense statements and other documents.
Biographical / Historical
Tasker Howard Bliss (December 31, 1853 - November 9, 1930), was a graduate of the United States Military Academy at West Point (class of 1875), inspector of European military schools in the late 1880s, military attaché to Spain at the outbreak of the Spanish-American War, served as Collector of Customs for Cuba and the Port of Havana from 1898-1902. He later was appointed governor of Moro Province in the Philippines and held other posts in the islands. He served as President of the Army War College on two separate occasions, and was named Army Chief of Staff in 1916, serving until May 1918. Personal papers at the U.S. Army Military History Institute (1871-1909).
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by Stanford University Libraries in 2014.
Bliss, Tasker Howard, 1853-1930
- Customs reports and Personal reports, Havana Cuba, January-April 1902, by Major, Commissary Subsistence, U.S.A. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence - Acting Collector of Customs, Havana, Cuba, April 1902 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Official telegram War Department, Headquarters Department of Cuba, Office of the Collector of Customs for Cuba, May 1902 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Major, Collector of Customs for Cuba, May 1-6, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence - Major, Collector of Customs for Cuba; Acting Collector of Customs for the Port of Havana; May 7-12, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence - Major, Collector of Customs for Cuba; Acting Collector of Customs for the Port of Havana; May 13-19, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence - Major, Collector of Customs for Cuba, May 18, 1902: many letters about leaving Cuba (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Address to those completing training as intelligence officers, General Staff in the army, n.d. - typescript (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Address, dinner of Council on Foreign Relations (published in its journal) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Address to Headquarters Department of Mindanao, Zamboanga, P.I. - typescript (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Graduation speech, Institute of Technology - typescript and handwritten (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Talk about problem of the Peace Conference - typescript (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Article published in The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, July 1905, p. 1 missing (Box 1, Folder 9)
- The Later Roman Empire by Tasker H. Bliss (Box 1, Folder 9)
- The important elements in modern land conflicts, by Brigadier-General Tasker Hl. Bliss, General Staff, U.S.A., President, Army War College (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Address to members of the America-Yugoslav Society (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Address at luncheon of the Union Inter-Alliee, in honor of Marshal Foch, Novermber 18, 1921 - typecscript and handwritten (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Chart of amounts paid and collected, dated May 3, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Statement of expenses of General T. H. Bliss, November 1902 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence from Charles Michaelson, New York World, March 14, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- The Armistices, published in American Journal of International Law, no. 2 Jackson Place - typescript with annotations (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Address, Institute of Politics - typescript (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Address, Business Men's Luncheon Club in Baltimore - typescript with annotations (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Book review of the Study of War for Statesman and Citizen, typesecript andyt published in American Journal of International Law, January 1928 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Book review of Statemanship or War by General Palmer, to be published in American Journal of International Law (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Typed manuscript, 42 pp, possibly part of General Palmer's book (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Address to fellow members of the Council and guests - handwritten (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Address? - typescript and handwritten (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Military Schools of Germany - typescript 84 pp plus appendix (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Military Art - typescript 169 pp (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Publication: Discours prononce a la distribution des prix (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Publication: Customs tariff for posts in the isalnd of Cuba, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Letter authorizing tract on Magnolia Bluff near Seattle, Washington be a site for a military post on Puget Sound, March 2, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, January - June, 1905 - contents from a binder (Box 2, Folder 8)